thank you mr speaker
as early as speakers on behalf of the
labour party have said the labour party
supports this bill and as far as it goes
it does improve the prudential
supervision of insurance companies to
help protect new zealand consumers by
ensuring that those insurance companies
act prudently maintain prudent balance
sheets and don't fail
and that's important because insurance
companies are repositories of not just
contracts of insurance that people
expect them to be able to honour if they
have it if they die for example and have
life assurance
but also because insurance companies are
also repositories of money through
endowment policies and the like that we
need to ensure are robust now that's
good as far as it goes and i think it's
probably been brought forward because of
the effects of the global financial
crisis and the
failures that we've seen around the
world of some very large insurance
companies and the many billions of
dollars of cost that that has caused not
uh just to consumers through
insurers not being able to honour their
contracts of insurance but also because
also because taxpayers have had to bail
out those insurance companies
uh there well there have been actually
been some multi-billion dollar
investments in respect to some of the
insurance companies uh in the united
states
uh in in terms of the um
the the wider issue or in terms of how
this is done it's done by in increasing
the powers of supervision of the reserve
bank and they're the body that's been
given these increased supervisory powers
to maintain prudential supervision of
insurance companies
and the point that has probably been
made by some of the prior speakers in
respect of this is that there is a lost
opportunity here to actually go further
in respect of prudential supervision of
our banking sector and how this could
assist our export sector through
influence on monetary policy
at the moment the new zealand reserve
bank has a almost singular focus when it
comes to monetary policy on interest
rates they try to take
the excesses out of the economy by
putting interest rates up and therefore
suppressing consumption
to prevent asset bubbles or to
ameliorate the effect of asset bubbles
and to take the heat out of the economy
which is inflationary
their reliance on
on that single instrument has had a
detriment effect on the export economy
the export economy uh has in new zealand
suffered a number of detriments for
start the way in which we have
implemented monetary policy in new
zealand means that we have structurally
higher interest rates than our
competitors
so whether you're a farmer or you're
another exporter in the manufactured
goods area you're facing higher interest
rates in new zealand than are faced by
our competitors overseas that has a
number of detriments
the first is that the uh export or the
investor in a new zealand enterprise
is has has a has a higher cost structure
than their competitors overseas in
respect of interest rates so if this if
this was a manufacturer producing
widgets and all the other things were
equal the widget manufacturer in new
zealand has a higher cost structure
than their overseas competitor because
we've got structurally higher interest
rates and after this 20 years of current
uh monetary policy and its current
incarnation you do actually have to
question in my view whether the uh the
higher interest rates that we have
structurally in the economy now are
actually partly an outcome of current
monetary and reserve bank policy and
this legislation which changes the
prudential requirements for insurance
companies could have actually
taken a similar approach in respect of
banks
so as to introduce more tolls to the
reserve bank so that they don't have to
rely exclusively on the interest rate
tool
the second detriment is suffered by
new zealand
businesses as a consequence of those
higher interest rates
which you know which undermines their
ability to invest in productive plant
that we need to improve the the overall
productivity of the uh new zealand
economy
the second detriment is that you
actually are effectively uh creating an
unlevel playing field in a world where
you've got global flows of capital and
if you have a bidder for a new zealand
business that's profitable who is
sourcing their funds for that business
from an overseas source of funds they
pay a lower interest rate in their home
country than a new zealand borrower
can borrow in new zealand unless they're
a multinational like fonterra and they
borrow from the international market but
for a small to medium-sized business uh
facing competition from uh uh to for the
purchase of those same assets from an
overseas purchaser again if everything
else is equal if they're facing the same
wage cost the same sale price for their
goods the same cost of their raw
materials
if everything else is equal the new the
overseas buyer can afford to pay more
from that same productive new zealand
asset compared with the new zealand
purchaser of those assets because the
overseas purchaser has a lower cost of
funds so all other things being equal
because they can afford to pay a higher
capital sum for that same business
enterprise and i just don't think that
that's in the long term interest of new
zealand so we actually need to have some
mechanism a different mechanism for the
reserve bank to take the pressure off
the interest rate device we also know
that the sole reliance on the interest
rate device according to the exporters
is causing volatility in our exchange
rate
which is difficult for them the
volatility of the new zealand exchange
rate is extreme the new zealand currency
is the fourth most traded currency in
the world it's an astounding statistic
we have an interest our currency is
traded more than the indian rupee a
vastly bigger currency than new zealand
it's traded more than the brazilian real
it's traded more than the south african
rand these these are these are economies
that are vastly bigger than new
zealand's economy and yet there is more
trade in the new zealand economy and the
new zealand dollar than there is in any
of those currencies i think we're even
more traded than than the than the
russian
the russian ruble well uh perhaps it's
because we have uh we have we have
higher structural interest rates
structurally higher interest rates and
people are speculating on
on on their knowledge that the new
zealand reserve bank pulls that trigger
harder than most other countries in the
world have historically
so the exporters say we actually need
some more tools in the toolkits under
other than the interest rate and they
actually say that we need to be using
prudential tools in respect of
banks more than we do and that's why
this is relevant to this discussion
because here we have the reserve bank
been given more tools in respect of
credentials uh supervision of the
insurance sector and yet in the banking
sector we've actually we've got very
limited ways in which those prudential
tools can be used by the reserve bank
now the reserve bank's got two main
functions the first is
maintenance of stable prices and the
second is maintenance of stability in
the financial sector and there isn't
much doubt that although relative to the
rest of the world we did pretty well
during the global financial crisis we
still weren't perfect we had to have
government guarantees of banks
both in terms of their retail deposits
and their wholesale deposits and we had
to have the reserve bank also buying
packets of securities uh from financial
institutions so um so
you know the whilst we might have done
better relative to some other countries
partly because of the savings history of
australia and the strength of their
banks
um not because of our own new
zealand-based savings i would note um uh
it's it's it's true that we're not
perfect and i think it is worth
considering
increasing the powers of the reserve
bank in respect of not just insurance
companies but also banks so that they
can use prudential ratios to stop the
rapid growth to stop the rapid growth of
credit in times of um
in time and boom times because in new
zealand what we do is we ratchet up the
interest rate the interest rates that
new zealand borrowers including
exporters have to pay goes up their cost
structure goes up actually most of that
money ends up going overseas because
it's owed to overseas lenders it doesn't
stay in the new zealand economy
and the labor party believes that we
should actually be conferring and making
explicit that the reserve bank instead
of relying purely on interest rates
can actually have
can actually adjust prudential ratios
for the bank so that they actually have
to source more of the money offshore
they'll have sometimes they'll have
difficulty and we actually will stop
some of these flows of hot money in and
out of the country which is really what
caused the over-inflation of the
property market the over-inflation of
the new zealand property market was not
based on new zealanders saving more
money and therefore having more money in
the bank to spend on assets it was
actually because the the liquidity in
the new zealand economy increased
because of the banks borrowing a lot of
money offshore and lending it in new
zealand and that was good for the banks
they entered extra margin but it wasn't
good for the new zealand economy because
it inflated the property bubble and it
did uh it did add to the imbalance in
the new zealand economy so this bill is
good as far as it goes but the
government is missing an opportunity to
make it explicit that the reserve bank
can use prudential ratios for monetary
policy purposes they can only do that
tangentially at the moment they they can
only use prudential policy first and
foremost for the prudential supervision
of the bank we say they need to be doing
more than that and use prudential ratios
to control the growth of credit
uh thank you mr speaker
i call craig